# 哈喽 大家好 我是王刚
Hello, everybody. I'm Wang Gang.
# 本期视频我跟大家分享一道传统菜
In this video I'm going to share a traditional dish with you.
# 富顺豆花
Fushun Douhua (aka Fushun Tofu Pudding)
# 首先我们准备四川黄豆1200g
First, let's prepare 1200g of Sichuan soybeans.
# 同学们最好用非转基因黄豆
It's better to use non-GMO soybeans.
# 否则成菜不美观
Otherwise, the finished dish won't look good.
# 然后加入适量的清水清洗干净浸泡4个小时（冷水）
Then add some water to rinse and soak for 4 hours (cold water)
# 冬天浸泡则需要6个小时以上（冷水）
Or 6 hours if it's winter.
# 泡发的黄豆重量是原型的2-2.5倍
Soaked soybeans weigh 2-2.5 times as much as the original.
# 下一步开始磨豆浆
The next step is to mill the soybeans to produce the soy milk.
# 首先加入与黄豆8倍的清水
First add 8 times the amount of water as soybeans.
# 用料理机搅拌成豆浆备用
Blend into soy milk using a blender.
# 同学们切记水的重量最好是黄豆的7至9倍
Remember to use 7-9 parts water for 1 part soybean.
# 豆浆搅好之后倒入锅中
Stir the soy milk and pour it into the wok.
# 然后开火边煮边搅拌
Then boil it while stirring.
# 每一次搅拌都必须刮到锅底
You must reach the bottom of the wok at every stir.
# 由于豆渣很容易沉底
Otherwise the soybean residue will sink to the bottom.
# 必须随时搅拌才不容易煮糊
Keep stirring to prevent burning.
# 豆浆第一次烧开的时候要加入适量的清水
When the soy milk is boiled for the first time, add some water.
# 这样可以确保豆浆真实烧开
This will ensure that the soy milk is cooked properly.
# 没有煮开的豆浆含有毒素不能直接饮用
Uncooked soymilk contains toxins and cannot be consumed directly.
# 所以这一步的目的是确保豆浆两次煮开
The purpose of this step is to make sure the soy milk is boiled twice.
# 豆浆煮开之后下一步开始准备“沥豆渣”
Once the soy milk is cooked, the next step is to drain out the bean pulp
# 准备纱布一块放到盆中直接倒入豆浆
Put a piece of filter cloth in a bowl and pour it directly into the soy milk.
# 提起纱布即可分离出不用的豆渣
Lift the filter cloth to separate out unwanted residues.
# 如果此时盛出一小碗加入白糖即成甜豆浆
If pour out some soy milk and add sugar into it, it makes a bowl of sweet soy milk.
# 分离出来的豆渣再次挤压出剩余的豆浆
Squeeze out the remaining soy milk from the separated residues.
# 下一步开始兑盐卤水
Next, we'll start mixing the brine.
# 首先我们敲下1小块盐卤（约20克）
First we knock down 1 small piece of salt brine (about 20 grams)
# 放入水瓶中再加入大约6倍的温水
Put it in a water bottle and add about 6 times the amount of warm water.
# 然后晃动化开拌匀备用
Then shake to mix it up.
# 同学们盐卤具有一定的毒性和碱性
Remember the salt brine is slightly toxic and alkaline.
# 非专业人士请戴好眼镜和手套
For non-professionals, please wear glasses and gloves during the operation.
# 下一步开始“点豆花”
The next step is to start to salt the soy milk.
# 首先我们把豆浆倒回铁锅中
First we pour the soy milk back into the wok.
# 然后撇去表面的浮沫
Then skim off the foam from the surface.
# 再把刚才调好比例的“盐卤水”均匀的滴入锅中
Add the salt brine to the liquid evenly.
# 滴进锅中的盐卤水必须用漏勺推散拌匀
The salt brine that drips into the wok must be dispersed with a spoon.
# 否则无法观察豆浆的浓稠度
Otherwise, you can't see the consistency of the soy milk.
# 同学们此时的豆浆温度大约为95度
The temperature of the soy milk at this point is about 95 degrees.
# 温度不能过高或者过低
The temperature cannot be too high or too low
# 否则蛋白质无法完美的凝固
Otherwise, the protein wouldn't solidify perfectly.
# 盐卤水不能“滴”得太快
The brine should not "drip" into the liquid too fast.
# 否则成菜有涩味
Otherwise, the finished dish will have an astringent taste.
# 滴盐卤水的全过程大约为10分钟
The whole process of dripping salt brine takes about 10 minutes.
# 越到后期必须滴得越慢
you should add the salt brine drip more slowly as you get to the end of the process.
# 这样才能够集中精神观察豆浆的浓稠度
It's the only way to concentrate on the consistency of the soy milk.
# 点豆花儿就像我们追梦一样
Salting the soy milk is like chasing our dreams.
# 一定要给以足够的耐心
You have to be patient.
# 因为成功的美食根本没有捷径可走
Because there are no shortcuts to make a successful meal.
# 直到最后豆浆中会产生明显的白色絮状即可
In the end, there will be a visible white flocculation in the soy milk.
# 然后开微小火慢慢将温度提升起来
Then turn on the heat and slowly raise the temperature.
# 保持未开的状态10分钟
Leave it unboiled for 10 minutes.
# 这一步的目的有利于蛋白质彻底的凝固
The purpose of this step is to facilitate complete protein coagulation.
# 蛋白质凝固之后周围的窖水会逐渐变成清澈的淡黄色
As the protein solidifies, the water around the pudding gradually turns clear and has a light yellow colour.
# 然后用漏勺或者筲箕对立挤压
Then squeeze wedges with a spoon or a sieve.
# 同学们切记这一步必须慢慢挤压
Remember to squeeze slowly at this step.
# 否则很容易浑汤
Otherwise, the soup may get muddy.
# 对立挤压的目的是让豆花能够充分的粘合成整体
The purpose of opposing extrusions is to allow the pudding to fully bond as a whole.
# 挤压成型之后用竹片将豆花“垫起来”
After extruding, "pad" the pudding with bamboo sheets.
# 这样的目的是保证豆花不被冲散
This is to ensure that the pudding doesn't get washed away.
# 然后再稍微挤压即可
Then just squeeze it a little more.
# 但挤压得越紧
But the tighter you squeeze.
# 成品的豆花就会越老
The finished tofu pudding will taste firmer
# 反过来压得越轻
in the contrary, the lighter you press.
# 豆花则越嫩
The more tender the pudding is.
# 最后开微小火保温即可随时食用
turn on low heat to keep the dish warm and ready to serve.
# 下一步我们开始制作蘸水“3件套”
Next we'll start to make the "3-piece" dipping set.
# 第1件是糍粑辣椒
The first one is patty chili.
# 首先锅中加入适量的干小米辣
First of all, add some dried "Xiaomila" chili pepper to the pan.
# 加入适量的灯笼椒
Add an appropriate amount of "Denglongjiao" (aka lantern chilis)
# 加入适量的子弹头
Add the right amount of "Zidantou" chili pepper
# 然后加入适量的清水清洗干净
Then add some water to rinse it off
# 这三种辣椒的作用分别是
The purposes of adding these three types of peppers are
# 小米辣调节辣度
Adding "Xiaomila" chili pepper to adjust spiciness
# 灯笼椒增加蘸水的香味
Denglongjiao (aka lantern chilis) to add aroma to dipping
# 子弹头调节蘸水的颜色
Zidantou chili pepper to adjust the colour of the water
# 清洗干净之后捞出重新加水开小火煮15分钟
Rinse and remove the chilies from the water, then add water to them in the wok and cook on low heat for 15 minutes.
# 这一步的目的是把干辣椒煮软
The purpose of this step is to soften the dried chillies
# 方便剁成糍粑辣椒
and to make them easier to be chopped into patty chilies.
# 辣椒煮至略软之后捞出剁成糍粑辣椒备用
Cook the chili until slightly soft, then drain off the water and chop the chilies into patty chili for later use.
# 同学们此过程最好戴上眼镜和手套
Remember to wear glasses and gloves in this process.
# 防止辣手和误喷眼睛
to prevent spiciness on the hands and accidental spraying into the eyes.
# 然后耐心的将辣椒剁成细蓉即可
Then patiently chop the chillies into a fine paste.
# 下一步开始调味
The next step is seasoning.
# 碗中加入适量的八角粉
Add the anise powder to the bowl to taste
# 加入适量的干沙姜粉
Add a generous amount of dry sand ginger powder
# 加入适量的干花椒面
Add a generous amount of dried and fine Sichuan peppercorn
# 加入少许的胡椒粉
Add a pinch of pepper powder
# 最后加入两勺食用盐（根据口味放）
Finally add two tablespoons of table salt (to taste)
# 然后搅拌均匀备用
And then stir them together.
# 嫌麻烦的同学也可以直接加五香粉
You can also add five spice powder if you'd like
# 下一步开始准备第2件套 香料酱油
Next, let's start preparing the second set: Spices and soy sauce.
# 碗中加入几颗八角（约8克）
Add a few star anise to the bowl (about 8 grams)
# 加入适量的桂皮（约10克）
Add a generous amount of cinnamon (about 10 grams)
# 加入两颗去籽的草果（约4克）
Add two seeded grass nuts (about 4 grams)
# 加入1小块陈皮（约5克）
Add 1 small piece of orange peel (about 5 grams)
# 加入几颗丁香（约1克）
Add a few cloves (about 1 gram)
# 加入几片香叶（约1克）
Add a few leaves of bayleaf (about 1 gram)
# 加入适量的干沙姜（约15克）
Add a generous amount of dried ginger (about 15 grams)
# 加入青花椒1小把（约10克）
Add 1 small handful of green Sichuan peppercorn (about 10 grams)
# 加入适量的小茴香（约10克）
Add a generous amount of cumin (about 10 grams)
# 加入适量的白芷（约5克）
Add a generous amount of baizhi (about 5 grams)
# 加入香果1颗（约3克）
Add 1 spiced fruit (about 3 grams)
# 最后加入适量的白扣（约4克）
Finally, add a generous amount of baikou (about 4 grams)
# 然后加入适量的开水浸泡10分钟
Then add some boiling water to soak for 10 minutes
# 这一步的目的是去除香料的苦涩味
The purpose of this step is to remove the bitterness of the spices
# 10分钟之后捞出放入锅中
Remove the spices from the water and add them to the wok after 10 minutes.
# 加入适量的生抽酱油（约1200克）
Add a generous amount of light soy sauce (about 1200g)
# 然后加入适量的清水中和咸味（约150克）
Then add some water to neutralize the saltiness (about 150g)
# 同学们如果酱油中含钠不高则不需要加水
remember not to add water if the soy sauce doesn't contain high amounts of sodium.
# 然后开火烧开3分钟即可倒出备用
Then turn on the heat and cook for 3 minutes.
# 倒出之后最好浸泡24小时
Soak for 24 hours after cooking.
# 这样更香
It smells better this way.
# 当然也可以立即使用
But of course, you can use it right away.
# 香料酱油完成之后开始准备第3件套姜葱油
After the spices and soy sauce are finished, let's prepare the third set of ginger and onion oil.
# 准备小葱1小把切成小段备用
Prepare 1 small handful of green onion, cut into small pieces for later use
# 准备洋葱1个切成细丝备用
Prepare 1 onion, finely chopped, for later use
# 当然也可以使用大葱
You can also use shallots, of course.
# 只要是葱都可以
Anything tastes like onions will do.
# 最后准备几块生姜切成姜片备用
Finally, prepare a few slices of ginger for later use
# 锅中加入适量的菜籽油（约1200克）
Add some vegetable oil to the pan (about 1200g)
# 油温烧至4、5成热之后下入切好的姜葱
Heat the oil until 4, 50 percent hot, then add the chopped ginger and onion.
# 同学们姜葱和菜籽油的比例大约为1：2
The ratio of ginger and onion to vegetable oil is about 1:2.
# 当然原料越多油则越香
Of course, the more ingredients, the better the taste of the oil.
# 姜葱熬制成金黄色之后捞出不用
cook the ginger and onions until golden brown.
# 下一步开始组合蘸水
Next, let's start assembling the dip.
# 首先在蘸碟中加入适量的糍粑辣椒
Start by adding a generous amount of patty chili to a dip dish
# 加入1勺葱油
Add 1 teaspoon of scallion oil
# 加入1勺熬好的酱油
Add 1 spoonful of the spice soy sauce
# 下一步开始加辅料
The next step is to start adding minor ingredients.
# 加入味精1小勺
Add 1 teaspoon of MSG
# 加入1小勺现剁的蒜蓉
Add 1 small spoon of freshly minced garlic
# 加入1小勺小米辣
Add 1 small spoon of "Xiaomila" chili pepper
# 加入少许葱花和藿香叶
Add a some green onion and Huoxiang leaves (patchouli leaves)
# 最后撒上适量的熟芝麻即可
Finish with a sprinkling of cooked sesame seeds
# 一份鲜香开胃的豆花蘸碟就制作完成
A delicious and appetizing dip is ready!
# 然后再盛上一碗滚烫的豆花即可享受勤劳带来的美味
Then serve up a bowl of hot tofu pudding and enjoy the delicious taste of hard work!
# 下一步开始技术总结
Let's start the technical summary.
# 第一
First,
# 原料最好选择四川本地黄豆
The best choice of soybeans is local Sichuan soybeans.
# 必须经过4个小时以上的泡发
Have to be soaked for at least 4 hours
# 才能够磨出高质量的豆浆
It's the only way to mill high quality soymilk.
# 夏天不能超过6个小时以上
No more than 6 hours in the summer
# 否则很容易馊（变质}
Otherwise it's easy to go bad
# 豆花的制作最离不开的是盐卤
Second, salt brine is essential for making soy bean pudding.
# 盐卤是四川自贡的特产
Which is a specialty of Sichuan Zigong.
# 制作豆花的盐卤必须用6倍的清水稀释之后才能够更好的使用
The salt brine for soy bean pudding must be diluted 6 times with water to make it suitable for use.
# 盐卤不能直接食用
Brine is not for direct consumption.
# 过量的误食可能会夺走人的生命
An overdose of mishandled brine can take a person's life.
# 且不能放在儿童能够触摸的地方
And keep it out of the reach of children.
# 第三
Third,
# 磨黄豆之前必须挑出劣质的黄豆
Before mill soybeans, you must pick out the bad ones.
# 这样才能够提升豆花的质量
This is what will improve the quality of the pudding
# 正常泡发的黄豆紧实有手感
Normal soaked soybeans are firm and tactile.
# 腐败的黄豆一捏就碎且有恶臭味
Rotten soybeans are crumbly and foul smelling.
# 黄豆和水的比例为8：1
The ratio of soybeans to water is 8:1.
# 以下为错误的示范
The following is a demonstration of a mistaken approach
# 豆浆太稀之后蛋白质会无法完全的凝固
When soy milk is too thin, the protein doesn't solidify completely.
# 表面会始终漂浮着一层白色的浮沫
The surface will always have a white layer of foam floating on it.
# 第四
Fourth,
# 豆花蘸水必须由糍粑辣椒、香料酱油、姜葱油组合而成
The dip sauce must be a combination of patty chili, spice soy sauce, ginger and scallion oil.
# 凡是加入辣椒油或者豆瓣酱均为不地道
Any addition of chili oil or doubanjiang is not authentic.
# 第五
Fifth,
# 传统工具的介绍
Introduction to traditional tools
# 此工具为石磨
This tool is a stone mill.
# 主要作用是磨豆浆和米浆
The main purpose is to mill soy milk and rice milk
# 在90年代以前几乎每家每户都有一套
Before the 1990s, almost every household had a set of
# 石磨在启动之前必须先用清水泡发10分钟以上
The stone mill must be soaked in clean water for at least 10 minutes before starting.
# 这样可以减少磨盘之间的石粉末掉下来
This will reduce the amount of stone powder falling between the stones.
# 此磨盘上下共计约重200公斤
The total weight of the stone is about 200 kg.
# 磨盘越大进豆量越多
The larger the mill, the more beans can be fed.
# 效率则越高
The more efficient it is.
# 磨豆浆需要两个人默契的配合操作
It takes two people to mill the soy milk.
# 其中一人负责推
One of them is responsible for milling.
# 另外一人负责加黄豆
One of them will add soybeans.
# 磨盘必须慢慢的转才能够充分碾压黄豆
The mill must be turned slowly to fully crush the beans.
# 推转得太快反而磨得更粗
If you push and spin too fast, the soybean won't be as fine.
# 第六
Sixthly,
# 此物为“粑杠”
This is a "Ba-bar."
# 主要用作捣碎糍粑辣椒
Mainly used for crushing patty chili
# 偶尔也会用来制作“糯米糍粑”
It's also used occasionally to make "mochi buns"
# “粑杠”下方的容器为碓窝
The container underneath the "Ba-bar" is the quern-stone.
# 主要用作于捣碎原材料
Mainly used for crushing raw materials
# 在没有工业化的以前
Before industrialization.
# 糍粑辣椒几乎是用碓窝捣碎
The patty chili is practically pounded with a quern-stone.
# 碓窝捣碎的辣椒会比机器和刀剁得更加“糍粑”
The patty chili will be more "patty" than the machine and knife.
# 其中“糍”的意思是指黏稠
The word "Ci" means sticky.
# “粑”的意思则是“贴得紧”的含义
Bameans "tightly attached."
# 第七 此物为“摇荡杆”
Seventh, this is a "swinging bars"
# 是用两根弧形木头中间由环形身体连接而成
It's made of two curved wood connected by a ring-shaped connection between them.
# 主要作用是挂上纱布
The main purpose is to hang the filter cloth.
# 沥出豆浆里面的豆渣
Drain the residue out from the soy milk
# 操作的时候动作类似摇摇荡荡
The operation move is swinging.
# 俗称“摇荡杆”
So they're called "swinging bars"
# 最后剩下的豆渣可以用来做菜
The soy residues can be used for cooking
# 也可以用作鸡鸭鱼猪饲料
Can also be used as chicken, duck, fish and pig feed
# 第七
Seventh,
# 过剩的豆花可以捞出放入纱布中充分的捣碎
The leftover tofu pudding can be spooned out into a filter cloth and well mashed.
# 然后封口旋转纱布挤干豆花里面的水分
Then seal and spin the filter cloth to squeeze the water out of the pudding.
# 最后用重物压制两个小时即成卤水豆腐
Finally, use heavy weight to press for two hours to make brine tofu.
# 富顺豆花的技术总结完毕
The technical summary of Fushun Douhua is finished
# 那杀牛都等得
It's easy to wait for a cow to be slaughtered.
# 啊 那杀牛豆等得 吃豆花等不得
It's easy to wait for a cow. You can't wait for the Douhua.
# 吃豆花就等不得
I can't wait to eat Douhua.
# 杀牛 牛杀了在它腿上
If you kill a cow.
# 皮刮了 割一坨就吃了
Scrape the skin, cut off a lump and and you can eat it.
# 你这个推豆花的过程好多嘛
But the process of making tofu pudding is so much longer.
# 所以说推豆花给你们吃的人
That's why if you find somebody who willing to mill the soybeans for you...
# 朋友或者亲戚一定要去珍惜他
A friend or a relative, you must cherish them.
# 吃还是好吃安 就是麻烦得很
It's so delicious, but it's a pain in the ass of making it.
# 嗯
Hmm.
# 富顺气候温和，四季分明，盛产大豆、辣椒和水稻
Fushun has a mild climate and four distinct seasons, which makes it an ideal place to produce soybeans, chili peppers and rice.
# 更是早在东汉年间，就因富世盐井成为井盐文化的发祥地
As early as the Eastern Han dynasty, the salt wells of the Fushi became the birthplace of the well-salt culture.
# 北周武帝天和二年，富顺因盐设县，豆花也因盐而发明
In theTianhe time of the Northern Zhou Dynasty, Fushun was established as a county because of salt, and "Fushun Douhua" was also invented because of salt.
# 富顺城以豆花兴，“富顺豆花”更以城为名
Fushun City is flourishing with "Fushun Douhua", and "Fushun Douhua" is also named after the city.
# 近一百年来，经过数位手艺人不断地传承和改良
In the recent hundred years, the "Fushun Douhua" has been continuously inherited and improved by several craftsmen.
# “富顺豆花”真正形成豆花、醮水、米饭三者合一
# 在这片土地上远近闻名，广泛传播，乡乡镇镇都开起了豆花店
Fushun Douhua is eaten with a combination of Tofu pudding, dip and rice.
Became well-known in this part of the land, many "Douhua" restaurants were opened in different towns and villages.
# 豆花也成为富顺人接宾待客的保留菜品，富顺县更是形成了“无豆花不成席”的风俗
Douhua has also become a traditional dish for the people of Fushun, and the custom of "no Douhua, no feast" has been formed in Fushun County.
# 一碗小小的豆花，香一座城；一门传承的手艺，造福一方百姓
A small bowl of Douhua fragrances a city; an inherited handicraft benefits the people.